嘿, 大家好
hey, what's up guys
我是Cherno, 欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
my name is Cherno, welcome back to my OpenGL series
那么, 我们上一次讨论了顶点缓冲区
so, last time we talked about vertex buffers
上面有个链接, 如果你没看过那个视频的话
there's a link up there, if you haven't seen that video
但实际上, 有一些部分我们忽略了
but there were some parts that we were missing to actually
得到三角形渲染
get our triangle rendering
并且特别是我们遗漏的两个主要部分
and specifically the two major parts that we were missing
就是顶点属性和着色器
were vertex attributes and shaders
今天, 我们将学习顶点属性
today, we're going to cover vertex attributes
所以, 什么是顶点属性
so, what is a vertex attribute
基本上就是, OpenGL管道的工作方式
so basically, the way that the OpenGL pipeline works is
我们在上一集稍微提到了一下
we've kind of discussed lightly in the last episodes
以后我们会有更深入讲解这个的视频
and we will have some kind of in depth video on that in the future
但是, 简单地说
but, to put it simply the way that
OpenGL管道的工作原理是我们为我们的显卡提供数据
the OpenGL pipeline works is that we basically supply our graphics card with data
我们在显卡上存储一些内存
we store some kind of memory on the GPU
它包含了我们想要绘制的所有数据
which contains all of the data of what we want to draw
然后我们使用一个着色器
and then we use a shader
是一个在显卡上执行的程序来读取数据
which is a program that is executed on the GPU to actually kind of read that data
并且完全显示在屏幕上
and display it on the screen more or less
通常我们画几何图形的方式
and typically the way that we actually draw geometry
就是使用一个叫顶点缓冲区的东西
is we use something called a vertex buffer
这基本上是存储在显卡上的内存缓冲区
that is basically a buffer of memory that is stored on the GPU
所以, 当对着色器编程时
so, when the program the shader
实际上, 是从读取顶点缓冲区开始的
actually starts to read that vertex buffer
它需要知道缓冲区的布局
it needs to know the layout of that buffer
这个缓冲区实际上包含的就是
what is actually contained in the buffer is it
只是一堆浮点数
just a bunch of floats
它们指定了每个顶点的位置
which dictate the position of each vertex
你也有纹理坐标, 法线之类的吗
do you also have texture coordinates, normal, anything else like that
所以实际上, 我们不得不告诉OpenGL
we have to actually tell OpenGL
内存中有什么, 又是如何布局的
what is in the memory, and how its laid out
因为如果我们不这么做, 那么
because if we don't do that, then
至于OpenGL, 只能看到它只是一堆字节
as far as OpenGL can see it's just a bunch of bytes
这和c++是一样的, 对吧
it's the same as with c++, right
我的意思是, 如果我写一个浮点数, 然后给它赋值
I mean if I write a float, and I assign it something
我们知道内存中有一个浮点数
we know that the memory there is a float
因为我告诉c++，这是一个浮点数
because I'm telling c++ this is a float
如果我把它转换成一个整数
if I cast that to an integer by the boy
我将它转换为一个整型指针
I cast it to an int pointer
如果我取浮点数的内存地址
if I take the memory address of the float
并将其转换为整型指针
and cast it to an int pointer
然后解引它
and then dereference it
我将得到完全不同的东西
I'm going to get something completely different
因为它对这块内存做了不同的解释
because it's interpreting the memory differently
这和这里的情况是一样的
that's kind of the same thing that's going on here
所以我们需要能够告诉OpenGL
we need to be able to tell OpenGL
前12个字节是三个浮点数
the first 12 bytes are three floats
并且每个浮点数三个字节
four bytes per float
并且, 这就是我的观点
and that is my position
之后的八个字节是我的纹理坐标
the next eight bytes after that are my texture coordinates
我有一个浮点数x和一个浮点数y或
I've got one float for x and one float for y or
u或者v, 如果你喜欢这么叫它的话
u and v, if you want to call it like that
所以我们需要一种方法能够告诉OpenGL
we need a way to be able to tell OpenGL
这是我的内存布局, 并且这也正是
this is the layout of my memory, and that is exactly
这整个VertexAttribPointer可以为我们做的一切
what this whole VertexAttribPointer thing can do for us
OpenGL中有一个叫glVertexAttribPointer的函数
there's a function in OpenGL called glVertexAttribPointer
这就是我们今天要讲的内容
that's what we're going to be taking a look at today
从着色器的一边来说
from the shader side
你也需要匹配你在CPU端定义的布局
you also need to match the layout that you define on the CPU side
在c++方面也是如此
on the c++ side as well
那么当我们在下一集介绍着色器的时候
and when we actually introduce shaders in the next episode
我们也会看一个那到底是怎么样的基本例子
we'll take a look at a basic example of what that looks like as well
再说一次, 我只是从最基本的例子开始
and again I'm just starting off with really basic examples
这样你就能看到它最简单的形式
so that you can see what it is like in its simplest form
但随着系列的继续
but as the series goes on
我们显然会增加它, 让它变得更复杂
we are obviously going to ramp it up, and make it way more complicated
我只是想让你们慢慢开始
I'm just kind of starting you guys off gently
好了, 别瞎扯, 继续
all right, without just rambling on, further
让我们看一下代码
let's take a look at the code
所以, 从上一集开始, 我们在这儿有浮点数组positions
so, from last episode, we have basically a float array of positions here
你可以考虑一下我这样划分的方式
you consider the way that I've kind of divided it is that
这里的每一行都是一个实际的顶点, 对吧
each line here is an actual vertex, right
所以我们有三个顶点位置
so we have three vertex positions
我们有三个顶点
we have three vertexes
这就是我们顶点在屏幕上的xy坐标
this is the x coordinate, this is the y coordinate of our vertex on our screen
在我继续之前
now before I go on
事实上, 我只是想定义顶点是什么意思
I just really want to define what I mean by vertex
因为人们似乎对此很困惑
because people seem to get pretty confused with that
并且也在错误地使用这个词
and also use that word incorrectly
顶点与位置无关, 对吧
a vertex has nothing to do with the position, right
顶点就是几何图形上的一个点
a vertex is just a point that is on your geometry
大多数人在视觉上对它们的明显印象是通过它的位置
the way that most people think about them visually obviously is by its position
所以如果我给你画一个三角形, 你会看到, 啊, 三个顶点
so if I draw you a triangle you'll be like, ah, three vertices
但顶点不
but vertices don't
顶点不是位置, 明白吧
vertices are not positions, right
一个定点不是一个位置
a vertex is not a position
一个顶点可以不仅仅包含一个位置
a vertex can contain way more than just a position
所以, 如果你告诉我, 嘿
so, if you tell me, hey
我有一个顶点, 它是0.5 0.5
I have a vertex, it's 0.5 0.5
这没有告诉我任何东西, 对吧
that doesn't tell me anything, right
因为你是在暗示
because you're kind of implying that
我指的是顶点位置
I mean vertex position
是的, 很多人都是这样用的
and yes, a lot of people do use it like that
这并不完全正确
that's not exactly correct
因为顶点可以包含比位置更多的数据
because a vertex can contain way more data than just a position
虽然它通常包含一个位置
although it does usually contain a position
所以, 我只是想说清楚
so, I just want to make that clear
当我说顶点位置时
when I say vertex position
我真正的意思不会只是
that's what I really mean I'm not going to just
实际上, 如果我说什么顶点时
if I actually say that what vertex
我指的是构成顶点的所有数据
I mean the whole blob of data that makes up that vertex
这也可能包括位置
which again could include the position
纹理坐标, 法线
texture coordinates, normals
颜色, by normrs, 切线
colors, by normals, tangents
诸如此类的东西
all of this kind of stuff
对, 它们可能都在一个顶点上
right, that could all be in a single vertex
所以, 只有位置
so, just the position
如果你只是涉及到位置
if you're just referred to the position
你应该叫它位置, 顶点位置
you should really call it positional, vertex position
所以, 这就是为什么我把这个浮点数作为一种位置
so, that's why I've got this float here as kind of positions
而不是顶点
not just vertices
因为, 现在, 它们只是位置
because, at the moment, they're just positions
尽管, 当我往里面添加东西的时候
although, when I add stuff to them
我真的可能应该给它们重命名
I really probably should rename them,
不管怎样, 我们有这三个顶点
anyway, so we have these three vertices here
然后我们生成一个缓冲绑定
and then we're generating a buffer binding
然后把这个或者
and then actually putting this kind of or
我应该说把这些positions复制到我们在这里定义的缓冲区中
I should say copying these positions into this actual buffer that we've defined here
通过指定一个指向它们的指针
by just specifying a pointer to them
以及它们有多大
and how big they are
这就是我们到目前为止所做的
and that's it that's all we're doing so far
再说一次, OpenGL不知道
so again, OpenGL has no idea
如果你看这段代码, 我们可以清楚地看到
that if you look at this code we can clearly see
好吧, 我们每个顶点有两个浮点数
okay, so we have two floats per vertex
这是位置的xy坐标, 对吧
and that is the x and y position, right
OpenGL不知道, 这对你来说可能很明显的东西
OpenGL doesn't know that, it might seem obvious to you
因为你看着这段代码, 你会想
because you're looking at this code and you're like
OpenGL怎么可能不知道呢
well, how can OpenGL not know that
但如果我突然引入第三个坐标呢
but what if I suddenly introduce a third kind of coordinate, right
所以, 换句话说
so, in other words
如果我想要一个三维的坐标系而不是二维的呢
what if I want a three dimensional coordinate system instead of two dimensional
就像我们这里一样
like we've kind of got here
如果我这样做呢
what if I do this
那么突然
well then suddenly
你知道, OpenGL是怎么知道的
you know, how does OpenGL know
实际上我有三个三维坐标系统的顶点
that I've actually got three vertices of a three kind of dimensional coordinate system
而不是只有一个
instead of just one
2 3, 然后是4, 还有一半, 我猜就是
2 3, and then kind of four, and a half I guess of just
两个坐标,对吧
two coordinates, right
因为如果我要重新排列这些代码
because if I was to rearrange this code
那么突然
well then suddenly
看起来我们实际上有三个以上的顶点
it looks like we actually have more than three vertices here
如果你坚持二维法则, 对吧
if you kind of stick to the kind of two dimensional rule, right
所以我想说的是我们需要告诉OpenGL, 外面的数据布局
so what I'm kind of getting at is that we need to tell OpenGL, out layout
这就是我们要做的
and that's what we're about to do
那么如果我们向下滚动一点
so if we scroll down a little bit
一旦我们绑定了缓冲区
once we kind of bind the buffer
并且我们用数据填充它
and we fill it with data
你没必要这么做
you don't have to do this
在用数据填充之前
before you fill it with data
你没必要这么做
you don't have to do it
之后只要缓冲区是实际绑定的, 就可以这样做
after you can do it whenever as long as the buffer is actually bound
那时我们就可以告诉
that is when we can tell
OpenGL, 我们缓冲区的布局是什么
OpenGL what the layout of our buffer actually is
这就是我们做那个的主要方法
and the main way that we do that
当打开我最喜欢的文档网站docs.gl
if I Just open up my favorite documentation website here, docs.gl
我们需要写两行代码
there are two kind of lines of code that we have to write
最重要的是glVertexAttribPointer, 就在这里
the most important one though is glVertexAttribPointer which is right over here, right
我将点击gl4链接
I'll click on the gl four link
我们可以看到这里有什么
and we can see what we have here
所以它需要很多参数
so it takes quite a few parameters in
总的来说, 就是index(索引), size(大小), type(类型)
by the index, size, type
normalized(标准化), stride(步幅)和pointer(指针)
normalized, stride and pointer
那么, 让我们快速地过一遍
so let's go through them really quickly
所以index是
so the index is the
需要再次修改的共享信息顶点属性的索引
index of the share info vertex attribute to be modified again
这没有多大意义
this doesn't make much sense
如果你不知道这是怎么回事
if you don't know how this works
基本上, 我们的着色器读取所有这些的方式是通过索引, 它是一个快照
basically, the way that our shader reads all this is by an index, it,s a picture
它几乎像一个数组
it is almost like an array
但数组中的类型可能不同
but the types in the array might be different
这是一个索引, 表示你实际引用的是哪个属性
so, this is an index as to which attribute you're actually referring to
顺便说一下, 所有这些都被称为属性
all of these things by the way are called attributes
并且这是我以其他方式提到的
and otherwise when I mentioned that
顶点不仅仅由位置组成
a vertex is made up of more than just position
对吧, 可能是位置
right, might be position
纹理坐标, 法线, 颜色等等
texture coordinates, normal, colors whatever
这些中的每一个就和位置一样, 都是一个属性
each one of those like a position is an attribute
颜色是一种属性
a color is an attribute
纹理坐标是一个属性
a texture coordinate is an attribute
法线是一种属性, 它们都是属性
a normal is an attribute, they're all attributes
所以, 这个index就是告诉我们, 嘿
so, this index is just telling us, hey
这个属性的索引是什么
what index is this attribute at
我这样说的原因是
the reason I say this is because
一般来说, 如果我们有一个位置
typically if we have like a position
例如, 在索引0处
for example, at index zero
我们需要把它作为索引0来引用
we need to be able to refer to it as index zero
那么, 我们来描绘一下吧
so, let's just picture this right
我有三种属性, 位置, 纹理坐标和法线
I have three kind of attributes, I have position, texture coordinate and normal
我需要能够说, 我想让我的位置在下标0处
I need to be able to say that I want my position to be at index zero
纹理坐标在索引1, 法线在索引2
my texture coordinate at index one, and my normal to be at index two
所以当我开始从着色器和显卡读取数据时
so that when I kind of start reading stuff from the shader side from the GPU side
然后进入那个缓冲区
and I go into that buffer
我可以简单地引用它们
I can simply reference them by
嘿, 请给我2号索引
hey, index two please
然后, 我发现这将是我的法线
and I noticed that will be my normal
因为我已经定义了那个缓冲区的布局
because I've kind of defined that layout
这就是index(索引)
that's what an index is
它只是缓冲区中实际属性的索引
it's just the index of that actual attribute in your buffer
这里的size可能有点误导人
size here can be a bit misleading
它是每个通用顶点属性的组件数
it's the number of components per generic vertex attribute
你可以看到, 这里写得很清楚
you can see that it says here clearly
它只能是1 2 3 4
that it must be 1 2 3 4
所以, 这个size和字节没有关系
so again, this size has nothing to do with bytes
或者和它们实际占用了多少内存也没关系
or like actual how much memory these occupies
它基本上是计数
it is basically the count
所以我的意思是, 当我们在这里指定type时
so what I mean by that is when we specify the type here
比如我们实际的顶点位置, GL_FLOAT(浮点型)
such as our actual vertex positions GL_FLOAT
这就是提供的浮点数的数量
this is how many floats were providing
显然这儿, 我们每个顶点有两个浮点数
so here clearly, we have two floats per vertex
所以这个size是2
so this size will be two
因为我们提供了一个两个分量的向量来表示我们的位置
because we're basically providing a two component vector that represents our position
如果我们切换到我之前提到的那种3D坐标系
if we switch to that kind of 3D coordinate system as I mentioned earlier
我们会把它设为3
we would be setting it to three
因为这个属性有三个浮点数
because we have three floats for this actual attribute
好吧, 所以type如同我刚才解释的, 就是
all right, so type as I just explained is
基本上就是我们提供的数据类型
basically the type of data that we're providing
GL_FLOAT是我们需要的
GL_FLOAT is what we want
normalized(标准化)，这有点棘手
normalized, this is a little bit more tricky
我们真的不需要特别担心这个, 如果我们做
we don't really need to worry about this particularly, if we do
如果我们处理的是浮点数, 因为它们已经被规范化了
if we're dealing with floats, because they already are normalized
但基本上这是用来
but basically this is used for
假设我们要指定一个字节
let's just say that we're specifying a byte
在0到255之间
that is between zero and two fifty five
因为这是我们颜色的值
because that's our color value
它需要被规范化到0到1之间, 在我们的实际着色器中作为一个浮点数
that needs to be normalized to be between zero and one, as a float in our actual shader
并且这就是我们实际要做的
and this is what we'll actually do it for us
基本上, 这不是一个例子
so basically, this isn's an example of something
这不是一个你可以在CPU上自己做的事情
that you can do yourself on the CPU side
但你也可以让OpenGL替你做
but you can also let OpenGL do it for you
如果你比较懒惰的话
if you're lazy
或者如果你有点
or if you're kind of
如果你只想让OpenGL为你做
if you just want OpenGL to do it for you
所以我们将把这个设为false, 或者是指定的GL_FALSE
so we'll be setting this to false, or specifically GL_FALSE
因为normalized实际上是一个整数GL_BOOLEAN
because normalized is actually a GL_BOOLEAN which is just an integer
好了, 继续
all right
stride指针, 这是很多人感到困惑的地方
stride pointer, this is where a lot of people get a little bit confused
所以我想澄清一下
so I want to just be clear on this
如文档所述, stride就是
stride is, as the documentation states
连续通用顶点属性之间的字节偏移量
the byte offset between consecutive generic vertex attributes
这个措辞就是
this is worded in
不太清楚他们为什么这样描述它
not sure why they worded it like this
但基本上, stride就是
but basically, what the stride is
就是每个顶点之间的字节数
is the amount of bytes between each vertex
所以, 在我们的例子中, 这是一个虚构的例子
so again, in our example, now kind of made-up example
如果我们有一个位置
if we have a position
我们有一个纹理坐标和一个法线
we have a texture coordinate and we have a normal
我们说, 位置是一个三个分量的向量
let's just say, the position is a three component vector
纹理坐标是一个两个分量的矢量, 或者两个浮点数
the texture coordinate is a two component vector, or two floats
并且法线也是三个分量
and then the normal is three components once again
明白吧, 所以, 我们有三个浮点数(位置)，一共12个字节
right, so we have three floats that's 12 bytes
加上纹理坐标的两个浮点数
plus two floats for the texture coordinate
那是另外8个字节, 所以我们在20个字节上
that's another eight bytes, so we're on 20 bytes
然后法线再加12个字节
and then another 12 bytes for the normal
所以一共32字节, 这就是我们的stride
so 32 bytes, that is our stride
因为它是每个顶点的字节大小
because it's basically the size of each vertex
这很重要的原因是因为, 如果OpenGL
the reason this is important is because if OpenGL
并且这也是它被称为stride的原因, 是因为
and the reason it's called stride as well is because
如果我们想从一个顶点跳到下一个顶点
if we want to jump from one vertex to the next
所以, 例如, 我想查找索引1
so, for example, I want to look up index number 1
从0开始, 0是第一个顶点
so from 0, 0 is our first vertex
我想跳到第二个顶点, 也就是索引1
I want to jump to our second vertex which is index number 1
我需要在缓冲区中加上32个字节
I need to go plus 32 bytes into the buffer
所以, 如果我们有一个指针, 指向缓冲区的开始
so, if we have a pointer to the beginning of our buffer
然后经过缓冲区的32个字节
and I go 32 bytes into it
我应该在下一个顶点的起点
I should be at the very start of the next vertex
这就是stride
that is what the stride is
所以, 记住这一点. 另一方面, pointer是
so, just remember that. the pointer on the other hand is
根据这个描述, 第一个组件的一个偏移量…
as this states, a offset of the first component of the
说实话, 我都不想读这个
I don't even want to read this to be honest
它是如此令人困惑
it's so confusing
pointer是指向实际属性的指针
pointer is a pointer into the actual attribute
所以, 这个已经在顶点的空间里了, 对吧
so, this is already inside the space of the vertex, right
所以你只是假装
so you're just pretend
不用担心有多少个顶点, 如果你有很多的话
don't worry about how many vertices, you have anymore
你就假装只有一个顶点, 我有一个顶点
pretend you only have one vertex, I have one vertex
在里面, 我有位置, 纹理坐标和法线
and inside there, I have position, texture coordinate, and normal
每一个的偏移量以字节为单位是多少, 对吧
what is the offset of each of those in bytes, right
所以, 对于位置, 偏移量为零
so, for position, the offset will be zero
因为它是缓冲区的第一个字节
because it's the very first byte of our buffer
我们实际顶点的第一个字节就是位置, 对吧
the very first byte of our actual vertex is the position, right
然后我们前进12个字节
then we go 12 bytes forward
我们到达了纹理坐标的开始
and we reach the beginning of the texture coordinate
所以, 对于我的纹理坐标属性
so, for my texture coordinate attribute
这个值(pointer)是12
this value would be 12
因为在12个字节处就是我们开始的地方
because 12 bytes into it is where we begin
并且最后再前进8字节
and finally eight bytes into that
我们得到顶点法线, 对吧
we get to the vertex normal, right
所以, 从开始算起第20个字节处就是顶点法线
so 20 bytes from the beginning is my vertex normal
所以, 对于顶点法线属性
so, for my vertex normal attribute
20是这个pointer的值
20 would be the value of this pointer
现在, 我们不再写0 12 20这样泛指的东西
now, instead of just writing generic things like zero, twelve and twenty
因为这可能会让人感到困惑, 而且不仅如此
because that can get a bit confusing, and not only that
但如果你重新安排布局之类的
but if you actually rearrange your layout or something like that
你得手动重新计算
you'll have to recalculate it all manually
这儿有一些宏, 以及
there are macros and kind of well
它确实是一个叫做偏移量的宏
it really is a macro called offset
实际上, 德国人用箭头算符证明了这一点
of actually, German demonstrated that in the arrow operator
如果你们看了我的箭头运算符的视频
if you guys watched my arrow operator video
那应该, 因为它对c++很重要
which is should because it's important for c++
我实际上演示了偏移
I actually kind of demonstrated offset off
实际上是我自己写的, 而不是用宏
I actually wrote it myself, instead of using a macro
但实际上, c++库
but the library actually, the c++ library
在状态库中会为你提供宏偏移量
in the state library provides you with an offset of macro
实际上, 你可以用它来
which you can use to actually
查找结构或类中某物的偏移量
find the offset of something in a struct or class
所以你也可以用同样的方法来处理stride,
so you can use things to kind of same with stride as well,
你可以使用宏之类的东西
you can use kind of macros and stuff like that
为你自己自动化这些东西
to automate this stuff for yourself
这样你就不用把值设置成
so that you don't have to just be putting values like
就像我刚说的12或32那样的stride
12 or 32 as I said for the stride
手动, 我只是向你解释应该怎么做
manually, I'm just explaining to you what actually should be
但就
but just
希望这完整地解释了VertexAttribPointer函数
hopefully this explains the entire kind of VertexAttribPointer function
因为这可能会让你困惑, 如果你才刚开始的话
because again it's something that can be confusing if you're just starting out
但它实际上非常简单, 并确保它是对的
but it is actually really simple, and make sure that it's correct
因为如果你在这里得到哪怕一个字节
because if you get even one byte kind of out of place here
你会得到一些奇怪的东西
you're going to get weird artifacts
可能在你的渲染中, 或者只在一个黑窗口中, 或者类似的东西
probably in your rendering, or just a black screen, or something like that
好了, 回到我们的代码中, 我们现在终于可以使用这个了
okay, so back here in our code, we can finally use this, now
所以对于这个已经绑定了的缓冲区我能做什么, 这很重要
so what I can do is with the buffer actually bound, that's important
我要写glVertexAttribPointer, 好了
I'm just going to write glVertexAttribPointer, all right
继续, 第一个参数是index
so again, first parameter is the index
现在, 这是一个非常简单的例子, 就像我之前提到的
now, this is a really simple case, as I mentioned earlier
我们只有位置, 所以首先
we just have positions, so first of all
我们只有一个顶点属性
we only have one vertex attribute
所以我们只需要调用这个函数一次
so we only need to call this function once
因为这里我们只指定了一个属性
because we're just specifying a single attribute here
这个index, 当然, 是0, 因为它是第一个属性
the index, of course, will be zero, because it's the first attribute
这个size, 记住size是指组件数量
the size, remember the size is the component count
与实际大小和字节无关
not anything to do with actual size and bytes
那么, 有多少个浮点数代表这个特定的顶点属性
so, how many floats represent this specific vertex attribute
2, 所以我就写2, 接下来
two, so am I write two, next we have
好吧, 这是一种…
well this one way
接下来是type
next we have the type
所以, 这就是我们这里的数据类型
so, this is going to be the type of data that we have here
显然, 它们都是浮点数
clearly they're floats
所以我们要输入GL_FLOAT
so we're going to type in GL_FLOAT
接下来, 我们要考虑是否要将它们标准化
next, we have whether or not we want them to be normalized
不, 它们已经是浮点型的了
no, they're already floats
它们已经在我们想要的空间中了, 所以是GL_FALSE
they're already in the space that we want them to be, so GL_FALSE
接下来是stride
next, we have the stride
正如我提到的
now as I mentioned
这个stride是每个顶点之间的字节数
the stride is the amount of bytes that we have between each vertex
这是第一个顶点, 第二个顶点, 第三个顶点
so this is our first vertex, second vertex, third vertex
显然, stride是两个浮点型的大小, 对吧
clearly, the stride is the size of two floats, right
所以我们可以写成8
so what we could write is just eight
基本上, 我们也可以写sizeof(float)*2
basically, we could also write size of float times two
这可能是我们实现自动计算的最好方法
and that's probably our best way to kind of automate that
也就是说, 让它尽可能的容易阅读
so to speak and make it as easy to read as possible here
因为我们处理的不是结构之类的东西
because we're not dealing with something like a structure or anything like that
最终, 当我们得到的不仅仅是每个顶点的位置
eventually when we have more than just kind of a position per vertex
我们开始引入像坐标和法线这样的东西
and we start to introduce things like that your coordinates and normals
我们会有一个结构, 组成一个独立的顶点
we will have a struct that makes up a single vertex
从这个意义上说, 我们可以把结构的大小作为一个stride传递过去
and in that sense, we could just pass in the size of that struct as a stride
这很好
and that would be fine
但现在, sizeof(float)*2
but for now, size of float times two
就是你需要向前移动到达第二个顶点的字节数
is how much you need to go forward to get to the second vertex
我只是把它说得非常清楚
and just to make that super clear
因为我们这里只有一个属性
because we only have one attribute here
这是我们到达第二个顶点所需要的字节总量
it's the amount that we need to go forward to get to the second vertex
而不是第二个属性
not the second attribute
明白吧
okay
那是下一个参数pointer
that's kind of what this next parameter is the pointer
记住, 你可以看到这实际上是一个指针
now keep in mind, you can see here that is actually a pointer
它接受的是一个指针而不是一个数字
it's taking in a pointer not a number
这可能有点令人困惑
so this might be a little bit confusing
但它仍然只是一个数字
but it is still just a number
因为记住指针是数字
because remember pointers are numbers
如果你不能完全理解指针
if you don't understand pointers fully
在上面观看我关于指针的视频
watch my video on pointers up there
因为这样你就清楚多了
because that's going to clear so much up for you
因为这个特殊属性是第一个
so since this particular attribute is the first
并且, 在这里, 这个属性是唯一一个
and in this case only attribute
这个是0
this is just going to be zero
你可以像这样传递它
and you can just pass it in like that
如果我们有另一个属性
if we had another attribute
举个例子
for example, let's just say
纹理坐标从这里开始或类似的东西
texture coordinate kind of started here or something like that
然后我们需要传递偏移量到那个纹理坐标
then we would actually have to pass in the offset to that texture coordinate
8个字节
which would be eight bytes
所以, 我们就可以像这样写上8
so we could just write eight like that
如果你试着这么做
if you try and do that
在这儿, 你会得到一个错误
you're going to get an error here
因为我们想传入8
because we're trying to pass in eight
然而它需要是一个常量void指针
and it needs to be a constant void pointer
解决这个问题的方法就是把8转换成一个常量void指针
the way you fix that is you just cast eight to a constant void pointer
我觉得有点不靠谱, 不过没关系
I see a bit dodgy or whatever, but it's totally fine
这就是你应该做的
that's what you're meant to do
当然, 如果你做得对的话
and of course, if you were doing this properly
你有一个真正的应用或者引擎之类的东西
and you had a real kind of application or engine or something like that
你可能需要一个结构来定义你的顶点
you would probably have a struct to actually define your vertex
然后你可以使用宏偏移量
and then you could just use the offset of macro
为了指出这对于来说是什么, 而不是只写8
to figure out what this is for you instead of just writing eight
或者类似的东西
or something like that
因为这
because that
这不可是好方法
that's not a good way to go
不管怎样, 对我们来说, 它是零
anyway, of course, for us it's zero
就这样, 就这样
there you go, that's it
这就是在这种情况下使用这个函数的方法
that's how you use this function in this case
它应该可以正常工作
and it should work just fine
但等等, 这儿总是
but wait, there is always
总是忘了一些东西
always something that I forget
你需要写一些东西才能让它运行
that you need to write to actually make this work
我总是忘记这一点当我开始写OpenGL的东西时
I always forget this when I start writing OpenGL stuff from scratch
因为很明显, 如果你和我一样
because obviously if you're kind of like me
你通常不会经常编写这样的代码
you don't typically write code like this often
因为这是你第一次做的事情
because this is something that you kind of do the first time
当你设置一个新引擎的时候
when you're setting up a new engine
然后你就忘了
and then you forget about it
但我们还需要一行代码
but there is one more line of code that we need
否则就会出现黑屏
otherwise we are just going to get a black screen
这就是
and that is
实际上, 我们需要启用顶点属性
we need to actually enable that vertex attribute
所以, 回到我们的文档中
so back in our documentation here
我真的希望这个文档能说
I really wish that this documentation actually said
关于启用或必须调用enable的一些事
something about enabling or having to call enable
事实上, 我不记得是否有
in fact I don't remember if it does
是的, 它说了
yeah, it does
最后, 它说
at the end, it says
要启用或禁用通用的顶点属性数组, 调用glEnableVertexAttribArray
to enable or disable a generic vertex attribute array, call glEnableVertexAttribArray
如果我们去看看这个函数
so if we go to this function
你会看到它能做什么, 它说…
you'll see what this does is it enables, it says blah blah
但基本上我们需要传入
but basically we take in
这就是我们了对这个函数感兴趣的地方
this is the function we're interested in
我们基本上只需要传入索引
we basically just take in the index
通用顶点的索引绝对是启用或禁用的
the index of the generic vertex is absolutely enabled or disabled
回到我们的代码
so back in our code
我喜欢在做指针之前先做这个
I like to do this before I do the pointer
这真的不重要
it doesn't really matter
OpenGL当然是一个状态机
OpenGL of course is a state machine
它不会检查它是否被启用
it's not like it's going to check to see if it's enabled
也不会去检查如果没有启动的话
and they're not do this if it's not
那样没关系
doesn't matter like that
你可以在任何地方调用它
you can call it anywhere you like
只要你的实际缓冲区是绑定的
as long as your actual buffer is bound
那么, 我们就去调用glEnableVertexAttribArray
so we're going to call glEnableVertexAttribArray
然后我们要启用的索引是0
and then the index we want to enable which is zero
好了, 就这样
okay, and that is it
在这种情况下, 这两行代码就是你需要做的全部
these two lines of code are all you need to do in this case
告诉OpenGL缓冲区的布局是什么
to tell OpenGL what the layout of our buffer is
理论上, 如果我们有一个着色器
and theoretically if we had a shader
下一集我们会讲那个
which we're going to have in the next episode
我们最终就可以在屏幕上看到三角形了
we'll be able to finally see our triangle on screen
在这儿
going up here
我要把这个小错误去掉
I'm just going to remove this little error here
这个多余的浮点数
this extra kind of float
我加进去只是为了演示
that I added just for demonstration
就是这样
and that's it
总结一下
so basically to summarize
这是我们今天写的代码
this is the code that we've written today
希望大家喜欢这个视频
hope you guys enjoyed this video
如果你喜欢的话, 就点击那个点赞按钮
if you did, hit that like button
你也可以加入我的discord
you can also go and join my discord a discord
blah blah
or confidenceer the channel become such discord
这基本上是一个社区
which is just basically a community of
人们在谈论这样的事情
people talking about stuff like this
你可以在那里讨论这一集
you can discuss the episode there
或者你也可以在下面的评论区留言
or you can leave a comment in the comment section below
如果你喜欢这样的话
if you prefer to do it that way
我真心建议你加入这discord
I really do recommend you join the discord though
这是一个很棒的社区, 你可以在那里提问
that's a great community of people where you can ask questions about
所有你在视频中见过的东西
everything that you kind of seen these videos as well as
你知道, 如果你的代码不能工作之类的, 你就会得到帮助
you know get help with your code not working or stuff like that
所以一定要加入
so definitely join up there
如果你真的想支持这个系列
if you really want to support the series
你想看更多的视频
and you want to see more videos
你想早点看视频
and you want to see videos early and
获得一堆其他类型的奖励
get a bunch of other kind of rewards
以及我实际上开始了一场聚会
as well as I've actually started doing a hangout
一个一个小时的聚会
a one-hour hangout
和所有的赞助人一起
with all of the patrons on a specific tier
我们聊上一个小时的话题
where we just basically talk about stuff for an hour
昨天刚办了一个, 很顺利
just did one yesterday went really well
所以一定要加入
so definitely join up there
如果你感兴趣的话, patreon.com/TheCherno
if you're interested in that patreon.com/TheCherno
这真的有助于支持这个系列
it really does help support the series
确保我能尽可能多地制作这些视频
and make sure that I can kind of keep making these videos as much as possible
下次我们会写一些着色器
next time we're gonna write some shader
那集可能会很长
it's probably gonna be quite a lengthy episode
因为实际上会有很多代码
because there is actually going to be quite some code
我需要去设置
we need to set up to
让着色器在OpenGL中编译和链接
actually get shaders to compile and link in OpenGL
但是一旦我们把它弄下来
but once we kind of get that down
我们终于就可以在屏幕上看到三角形了
we'll finally have our triangle on the screen
所以这应该是非常令人兴奋的
so it should be really exciting
下次见, 拜
I'll see you guys next time goodbye